

Networking, Cybersecurity, and Machine Learning Research

Ph: (+91) 79821 30021 Email: sgrover@protonmail.ch Web: https://sarthakgrover.github.io https://linkedin.com/in/groversarthak/

## Summary\_

I'm a network analysis and security researcher, and a machine learning enthusiast with 7+ years of experience specializing in home network measurement, IoT security, and Internet performance analysis. An expert at data analysis using python-pandas, SQL, and machine learning toolkits such as scikit-learn and TensorFlow. Currently working as a freelance researcher, I'm interested in measuring and securing the Internet using innovative machine learning solutions.

## **Education**

### MA (PhD Incomplete) in Computer Science

Princeton, New Jersey, USA

**Princeton University** 

Apr. 2016

- · Received research assistance for work on Network Performance Analysis and Home Network Security.
- Awarded STEM Chateaubriand Fellowship by the Embassy of France for work on the Internet of Things (2016).
- Advisor: Prof. Nick Feamster
- GPA: 3.8/4.0

## **BTech and MTech in Electronics and Communication Engineering**

Roorkee, INDIA

Dec. 2010

Indian Institute of Technology, Roorkee

- Specialization in Wireless Communication.
- Thesis: Performance Evaluation of Cross-Layer Wireless Body Area Networks.
- GPA: 8.06/10.00

## Work Experience \_\_\_\_\_

Sugandhaa Co., Ltd.

New Delhi, INDIA

Manager Apr. 2018 - Present

- Leading a family-owned business. Responsible for inventory, account management, and conducting sales.
- Proficient in interacting directly with customers and managing daily finances to ensure smooth business operations.

Freelance Researcher Dec. 2018 - Present

- **Network anomaly detection:** Designed and implemented an anomaly detection algorithm for NetFlow records. [Link]
- Used machine learning to extract and transform packet features and detect anomalous behavior in real-time.
- Successfully identified port scans and DoS activity using statistical, information-theoretic, and clustering-based approaches.
- CDN performance analysis: Conducted website measurements and tested performance of web page load times. [Link]
- Developed a scalable rule-based CDN estimation algorithm for websites using xcache, whois, parsing, and DNS information.
- Revealed that for some websites, performance can be substantially improved using CDNs offered by their own ASNs.
- Coursework: Awarded certificate for Neural Networks and Deep Learning by deeplearning.ai on Coursera.
- Awarded certificate for Functional Programming Principles in Scala by EPFL on Coursera.

[Link] [Link]

# **Princeton University**Graduate Research Assistant

Princeton, NJ, USA Jan. 2015 - Sep. 2017

• Advisers: Prof. Nick Feamster (University of Chicago) and Dr. Roya Ensafi (University of Michigan)

Advisers: Prof. Nick Feamster (University of Chicago) and Dr. Roya Ensañ (University of Michigan)
 Identifying Internet of Things (IoTs): Captured and analyzed packets from various IoT devices in the lab.

o. [Link]

- Used machine learning to extract and transform (FFT, PCA, MMT, KDE) volumetric and distribution features from packet headers.
- · Used clustering (kmeans, Spectral, MeanShift, DBSCAN) to identify IoTs, and distinguish activity and background traffic.
- Built an IoT behavior monitor and demonstrated that it successfully detects DDoS attack anomalies using DBSCAN. [Link]
- Real-time IoT query system: Developed a filtering algorithm to discard non-IoT network traffic using DNS queries. [Link]
- Implemented an exploratory ETL pipeline in PySpark to extract packet header features and cluster IoT network traffic.
- Internet of Unpatched Things: Tested multiple IoT devices in the lab and exposed their vulnerabilities. [Link]
- Found that PixStar's digital photo frame was susceptible to eavesdroppers and fails to encrypt photographs, and the Nest thermostat exposed private location information of nearest weather stations to the ISP (now patched).
- Broadband traffic analysis: Analyzed usage behavior of customers offered higher speed broadband without their knowledge.
- Found that difference in traffic demand was higher for moderate users as compared to high-volume subscribers. [Link]
- Presented at PAM (Mar 2016), CableLabs (Jul 2016), and FCC (Oct 2016).

[Link]

- Censor Planet: Developed scripts to analyze censorship data collected throughout the world using TCP SYN-ACK attacks.
- Implemented multiprocessing python code to filter, analyze, and recombine large traces of server responses to TCP packets.

• Used time-series analysis to conclude whether there is server-side blocking, client-side blocking, or no firewall. [Link]

OCTOBER 25, 2019 SARTHAK GROVER · RÉSUMÉ

### **Georgia Institute of Technology**

#### **Graduate Research Assistant**

Aug. 2012 - Dec. 2014

Atlanta, GA, USA

• Advisers: Prof. Nick Feamster (University of Chicago) and Prof. Renata Teixeira (INRIA Paris)

- **Home network analysis:** Analyzed active and passive network traces from multiple homes to study network availability and reliability in various countries, popular devices and infrastructure in homes, and traffic usage with time. [Link]
- Discovered most home traffic is exchanged to a small number of domains, and home network usage differs based on the device.
- Analyzed prevalence and persistence of traceroutes to a variety of Internet destinations from the perspective of access points.
- **SAZO:** Built and deployed a blacklist based malware identification and notification system on the home router. [Link]
- Used bloom-filters to index malicious IPs and perform quick look-ups on packet headers before redirecting traffic to DPI boxes.
- Facade: Built and deployed an HTTP pluggable transport protocol to avoid censorship and detection for Tor. [Link]
- Responsibilities included parallelizing code, implementing framing buffers, and unit testing the system in a team of 6 students.
- QoS control using SDN: Identified application and used SDNs to program appropriate rate shaper and control network flow.
- Identified traffic using a DNS classifier and demonstrated ad-block for the whole home using FlowQoS at the access point. [Link]

#### **Indian Institute of Science**

Bangalore, INDIA

Junior Research Fellow

Apr. 2011 - Dec. 2011

- Adviser: Prof. Anurag Kumar (Director, IISc Bangalore).
- WSNs for Societal Needs and Disaster Management: Prepared work-plan proposal for submission to the Department of Science and Technology (DST), Govt of India.
- Computed closed-formed expressions for network reliability for regular hexagonal network topology.
- · Evaluated information-theoretic bounds on network reliability for random hybrid network topology.

#### Indian Institute of Technology, Roorkee

Roorkee, INDIA

Graduate Research Assistant

Jul. 2009 - Dec. 2010

- Performance Evaluation of a Wireless Body Area Network: Implemented cross layer protocol to auto-regressively predict PHY parameters and control MAC level queue for mobile nodes in Rayleigh fading environment. Modeled human body channel for intra BAN (on-body network). Comprehensive simulations on NS2 showed improved network throughput and lifetime. [Link]
- Implementation of a Soft Decision Decoder using Trellis on FPGA: Implemented a real-time trellis decoder for BCH codes using VHDL on Xilinx ISE and configured it on FPGA.

## Internships

**Comcast**Philadelphia, PA, USA

Research Intern May. 2016 - Aug. 2016

- Advisers: Jason Livingood (VP, Comcast) and Nirmal Mody (Manager, Comcast)
- Customer Owned and Managed (COAM) Internet of Things (IoT) security: Used DPI to study connectivity, security, and privacy of a subset of Comcast smart homes. Developed a script to search for PII in unencrypted IoT data.
- Used DNS queries to filter smart homes. Identified a misconfigured XBOX for one subscriber by correlating IoT packet captures.

INRIA Paris, FRANCE

Research Engineer

May. 2014 - Sep. 2014

- Advisers: Prof. Renata Teixeira (INRIA Paris) and Dr. Christian Kreibich (ICSI Berkley).
- Browserlab: Home network diagnosis for performance bottleneck detection: Tested uplink and downlink broadband performance between devices, gateways, and online servers to detect if the bottleneck is in the local wireless network or at the edge router.

LIP6, UPMC Paris, FRANCE

### Research Engineer

Jun. 2013 - Sep. 2013

- Adviser: Prof. Renata Teixeira (INRIA Paris).
- Home network troubleshooting platform using Fathom and BISmark: Programmed active traceroute test on bismark router and analyzed latency and throughput performance from routers.

#### **North Carolina State University**

Raleigh, NC, USA

Research Associate

Dec. 2011 - Apr. 2012

- Adviser: Prof. Injong Rhee (VP IoT, Google).
- Indoor Localization for Samsung Smartphones using Radio: Implemented FM/AM transceiver systems on GNURadio to utilize the time difference in RDS information for performing accurate indoor localization on smart phones.

### **University of New South Wales**

Sydney, AUSTRALIA

#### Practicum Exchange Student

May. 2009 – Aug. 2009

- Adviser: Prof. Vijay Sivaraman (UNSW)
- Wireless Body Area Networks for Athlete Monitoring: Analyzed time-series experimental data collected from wireless bio-medical sensors. Developed encounter based model to capture user mobility, and generate synthetic network topologies. [Link]
- Modeled the evolution of connectivity with time, and computed correlation of connectivity using Cholesky decomposition.
- Evaluated the connectivity model using Kolmogorov-Smirnov (K-S) test. Publication awarded Best Paper at WiMob 2010.

October 25, 2019 Sarthak Grover · Résumé

## **Teaching Experience**

PRINCETON UNIVERSITY

**COS 126: Introduction to Computer Science**, Graduate Preceptor with Prof. D. Clark **Coursera MOOC: Fog Networks and IoT**, Teaching Assistant with Prof. M. Chiang

Spring 2015 Summer 2015

GEORGIA INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY

CS3251: Computer Networking, Teaching Assistant with Prof. P. Traynor

Fall 2013

Indian Institute of Technology

**ECE 102: Fundementals of Electronics**, Teaching Assistant with Prof. M.V. Kartikeyan **ECE 311: Principles of Digital Communication**, Teaching Assistant with Prof. A. Patnaik

Spring 2010 Fall 2009

## Awards & Certificates

2019	Neural	<b>Networks</b>	and Dee	p Learning,	Coursera
------	--------	-----------------	---------	-------------	----------

- 2019 Functional Programming in Scala, Coursera
- 2019 Machine Learning, Coursera
- 2016 STEM Chateaubriand Fellowship Award, Embassy of France
- 2010 **Best Student Paper Award**, IEEE Wireless & Mobile Computing, Networking and Comm. (WiMob)
- 2009 **Practicum Exchange Program Scholarship**, University of New South Wales, Sydney
- 2008 **Best Electronics Project**, Annual Hobbies Club Exhibition, IIT Roorkee
- 2004 **Ranked 14**, National Mathematical Olympiad (Delhi)

## Skills\_

**Programming** Python v2.7, v3.3 – v3.7, iPython v7.8, Scala v2.11, Java v12.0, PostgreSQL, C/C++, R, Matlab, Node.js

**Analytics** Pandas v0.13 – v0.23, Scikit-Learn v0.21, Tensorflow v1.14.0 – v2.0.0, Apache Spark, Numpy, Scipy, Matplotlib **Networking** Wireshark/Tshark v2.0, Iperf v2.0 – v3.7, Nmap v7.8, Scapy v2.4, Urllib3, Requests, Beautiful Soup 4, Networkx

Tools PyCharm, PyLint, IntelliJ IDEA SBT, Eclipse, Git, Linux, Adobe Photoshop, Corel Draw, MS Office, MFX

## **Selected Publications**

#### **CONFERENCE PROCEEDINGS**

A Case Study of Traffic Demand Response to Broadband Service-Plan Upgrades

Sarthak Grover, Roya Ensafi, and Nick Feamster

Proceedings of 17th International Conference on Passive and Active Measurement (PAM), 2016, Heraklion, Greece

Facade: High-Throughput, Deniable Censorship Circumvention Using Web Search

Ben Jones, Sam Burnett, Nick Feamster, Sean Donovan, Sarthak Grover, Sathya Gunasekaran, and Karim Habak 4th USENIX Workshop on Free and Open Communications on the Internet (FOCI), 2014, San Diego, CA, USA

FlowQoS: QoS for the Rest of Us

M. Said Seddiki, Muhammad Shahbaz, Sean Donovan, Sarthak Grover, Miseon Park, Nick Feamster, and Ye-Qiong Song Proceedings of the Third Workshop on Hot Topics in Software Defined Networking (HoTSDN), 2014, Chicago, IL, USA

Peeking Behind the NAT: An Empirical Study of Home Networks

Sarthak Grover, Mi Seon Park, Srikanth Sundaresan, Sam Burnett, Hyojoon Kim, Bharath Ravi, and Nick Feamster *Proceedings of the ACM Internet Measurement Conference (IMC)*, 2013, Barcelona, Spain

An Experimental Study of Wireless Connectivity and Routing in Ad Hoc Sensor Networks for Real-time Soccer Player Monitoring Vijay Sivaraman, Ashay Dhamdhere, Hao Chen, Alex Kurusingal, and Sarthak Grover

Ad Hoc Networking 11.3 (May 2013) pp. 798–817. Elsevier Science Publishers B. V., 2013

Performance Evaluation of Wireless Body Area Network using Cross Layer Approach Sarthak Grover

Master's Thesis, Indian Institute of Technology Roorkee (June 2010). 2010

Experimental study of mobility in the soccer field with application to real-time athlete monitoring

Vijay Sivaraman, Sarthak Grover, Alex Kurusingal, Ashay Dhamdhere, and Allison Burdett

2010 IEEE 6th International Conference on Wireless and Mobile Computing, Networking and Communications (WiMob), 2010, Ontario, Canada

A real time face tracking system using rank deficient face detection and motion estimation Vidit Saxena, Sarthak Grover, and Sachin Joshi

2008 7th IEEE International Conference on Cybernetic Intelligent Systems (CIS), 2008, London, U.K.

#### WORKSHOPS AND TALKS

#### The Internet of Unpatched Things

Sarthak Grover and Nick Feamster

Proceedings of FTC PrivacyCon, 2016, Washington, DC, USA

#### mPaaS: Delivering Mobile Platforms as a Cloud Service

Arpit Gupta and Sarthak Grover

10th USENIX Symposium on Networked Systems Design and Implementation (NSDI), 2013, Lombard, IL, USA

#### End-to-end Routing Behavior in the Internet: A Re-Appraisal from Access Networks

Sarthak Grover and Nick Feamster

ISMA Workshop on Active Internet Measurements (AIMS), 2013, La Jolla, CA, USA

#### Panoptes: Detecting Malware Activity in Home Networks

Sarthak Grover and Nick Feamster

HomeSys: Workshop on Design, Technology, Systems and Applications for the Home (UbiComp), 2013, Zurich, Switzerland

## **Extracurricular Activity**

#### **IEEE Student Chapter**

Roorkee, INDIA

Member & Treasurer

Jun. 2006 - Jun. 2010

• Organized events for student members to discuss recent research in the field of electronics and communication engineering.

**Geek Gazette** Roorkee, INDIA

### Founder & Chief Designer

Jun. 2008 - Jun. 2010

• Founded the campus technical magazine to publish recent influential research by university professors.

- Responsible for reading research papers, summarizing and editing articles, and designing the magazine in Corel Draw.
- Acquired publishing funds from the campus IEEE student chapter.

### **Watch Out News Agency**

Roorkee, INDIA

Chief Designer

Jun. 2005 - Jun. 2008

- Designer for campus news magazine. Promoted to Chief Designer in third year.
- Responsible for editing and designing magazine in Corel Draw, drawing cartoons in Adobe Photoshop, and hiring new designers.

### **Hostel Soccer Club** Regular Member

Roorkee, INDIA Jun. 2005 - Jun. 2010

• Member of hostel and academic year soccer clubs. • Regularly played defense and mid-field as part of the team.

SARTHAK GROVER · RÉSUMÉ OCTOBER 25, 2019